A Guide to the John Auer papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA147
Rockefeller Archive Center
John Auer papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff
1901-1931
Rockefeller Archive Center
Flexner, Simon
Rockefeller University
Auer, John
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA147
0.25 Cubic Feet
31 items and bibliography
Biographical/Historical note
John Auer, pharmacologist at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research from 1907 to 1921. Worked in the laboratory of his father-in-law, S.J. Meltzer.
Dr. Auer's association with The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research began with grant support for a three year period at $500 a year on researches with Dr. Prudden. When he joined the Institute he worked in the laboratory of S.J. Meltzer who was his father-in-law. His investigations were on: Digestion, respiration and heart. They also, studied the anaphylactic caused functional disturbances; physiological action of various drugs and many studies on war gas, tetanus, reflexes and connective tissue.
Biographical note
1875 Born March 30, Rochester, New York
1898 S.B. University of Michigan
1902 M.D. Johns Hopkins Medical School
1903 Married October 1 to Clara Meltzer of NYC Children: James, Helen, John
1902-1903 Medical House Officer, Johns Hopkins Hospital, Baltimore, Md.
1903-1905 Three year grant from RIMR through T.M. Prudden $500 for each year; Letter head at the address of 22 Mount Morris Park West, NYC suggests he and his wife Clara Meltzer Auer carried on the private practice of medicine at this period.
1906-1907 Instructor in physiology, Harvard Medical School
1906-1907 Resident Fellow, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
1907-1908 Assistant in Physiology, RIMR
1908-1909 Associate in Physiology, RIMR
1909-1921 Associate Member in Physiology and Pharmacology, RIMR
1921- Professor of Pharmacology and Director of the department St. Louis University School of Medicine
1924- Also Pharmacologist St. Mary's Group of Hospitals, St. Louis
1948 Died April 30
Member of: American Physiological Society, American Society of Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics; Secretary 1912-1916; President 1924-1927, Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine; Vice-President 1917-1919, Association of American Physicians, Harvey Society, St. Louis Academy of Sciences, St. Louis Medical Society, Maj. M.O.R.C. 1917-1922
Scope and Contents note
9 pages of bibliography.
The only pictures of Dr. Auer in the University photo collection are those with Dr. Meltzer's laboratory group. Dr. Auer has been identified by Dr. H. Kunkel.
Arrangement note
Arranged in chronological order.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 Au34
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Medical education; Flexner, Simon; Rockefeller University; Auer, John; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- John Auer papers (Box 1)
  - J.A. to L.E. Holt Thanks on appointment as Fellow 1904-1905, 1904 June 23
  - J.A. to S. Flexner Thanks on appointment to Asst. 1907-1908, 1907 April 25
  - J.A. to L.E. Holt Thanks on appointment to Asst. 1907-1908, 1907 April 29
  - J.A. to L.E. Holt Accept appointment as Associate, 1908 June 1
  - Bus. Mgr. to A.J. Sheldon. Introducing J.A., 1915 July 26; (carbon copy)
  - H. James to J.A. re intro to A.J. Sheldon, 1915 July 26; (carbon copy)
  - H. James to J.A. re assembly hall use, 1916 November 28; (carbon copy)
  - Bus. Mgr. to J.A. Ex. Com. vote to allow lectures for an honorarium, 1917 December 26; (carbon copy)
  - Acting Bus. Mgr. to J.A. with Dr. Flexner's request that only dogs immediately required be retained, 1918 July 25; (carbon copy)
  - S. Flexner to secretary, handwritten note re Ex. Com. consent to Auer lecture for honorarium, undated
  - S.A. Brown to S. Flexner appreciation of J.A., substitution in pharmacology course for Prof. Wallace, 1918 June 18; (carbon copy)
  - Acting Bus. Mgr. to J.A. re basement centrifuge room, 1919 January 2; (carbon copy)
  - H.D. Senior to S. Flexner re J.A. continued substitution for Dr. Wallace, 1919 January 31; (typescript signed)
  - Secretary to S. Flexner reporting J.A. willingness to continue substitution despite drain on time, 1919 February 1
  - S. Flexner to H.D. Senior Consent for J.A. to continue substitution, 1919 February 5; (carbon copy)
  - H.D. Senior to S. Flexner Thank you, 1919 February 6; (typescript signed)
  - Bus. Mgr. to J.A. on building places for equipment, 1919 August 14; (carbon copy)
  - Bus. Mgr. to J.A. request for suggestions for National Vigilance Committee, 1919 December 5; (carbon copy)
  - J.A. to L.E. Holt Acknowledgement of appointment as Assoc. Member, 1920 June 18
  - J.A. to S. Flexner resignation to accept appt at St. Louis University School of Medicine Aug. 1, 1921, 1920 December 7
  - J.A. to S. Flexner to discontinue for Mrs. Meltzer secretarial help, 1921 January 22
  - Secretary to J.A. Acceptance of resignation, 1921 January 24; (carbon copy)
  - J.A. to E.B. Smith on insufflations apparatus of Dr. Meltzer, 1921 September 21
  - Clara Meltzer Auer to Mr. Robertson thanks and return of Institute check after mother's death, 1923 January 8
  - S. Flexner to Clara Meltzer Auer sympathy on mother's death, 1923 January 11; (typescript copy)
  - Clara Meltzer Auer to S. Flexner thanks for sympathy letter, 1923 January 21
  - J.A. to E.B. Smith accepting designation as delegate of RI at inauguration of Dr. Hadley, 1923 November 5; (typescript signed)
  - J.A. to S. Flexner on type of animal incinerator in use at R.I., 1927 April 20; (typescript signed)
  - Asst. Bus. Mgr. to J.A. reply on animal incineratory, 1927 April 25; (carbon copy)
  - J.A. to Stanley Howe thanks for information on animal incinerator, 1927 April 29; (typescript signed)